<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><!DOCTYPE ecpc_EP SYSTEM "ep.dtd"><ecpc_EP><header language="EN"><title>CRE Thursday 27 January 2005</title>

<index>Index

<label>Debates</label>
<date>Thursday 27 January 2005 </date>
<place> Brussels</place>
<edition>OJ edition</edition>

<indexitem number="1">Opening of the sitting</indexitem>
<indexitem number="2">Documents received: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="3">Agenda: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="4">Statement by the President</indexitem>
<indexitem number="5">Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="6">Voting time</indexitem>
<indexitem number="7">Explanations of vote</indexitem>
<indexitem number="8">Corrections to votes: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="9">One-minute speeches on matters of political importance</indexitem>
<indexitem number="10">Verification of credentials: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="11">Communication of Council common positions: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="12">Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="13">Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="14">Dates for next sittings: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="15">Adjournment of the session: see Minutes</indexitem>

</index>

</header>

<body>

<chair>IN THE CHAIR: MR BORRELL FONTELLES
President</chair>
<omit>(The sitting was opened at 9.05 a.m.)</omit>

<heading number="1">Opening of the sitting</heading>

<intervention ref='1'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s1' language="UNKNOWN">Ladies and gentlemen, we will have to change the agenda, because, as I expect you already know, the President of Ukraine, Mr Yuschenko, cannot be with us today as planned, due to the weather conditions seriously affecting the whole of central Europe which have prevented him from taking off this morning.
</speech>
</intervention>

<heading number="2">Documents received: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="3">Agenda: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="4">Statement by the President</heading>

<intervention ref='2'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s2' language="UNKNOWN"> We had planned to dedicate a statement and a minute’s silence to the memory of the Auschwitz-Birkenau tragedy today and I believe we must go ahead with that.
Ladies and gentlemen, today is a sad day of commemoration for the whole of humanity. On a day like today in 1945 the soldiers of the Red Army liberated the Nazi extermination camp whose name has become engraved on man's collective memory. It has become engraved on our collective memory as the name of absolute horror, of evil, in its most extreme form, of industrialised, planned and documented crime.
We are still all astounded that it could have happened. But it did happen. It is unimaginable, but it was real. Today, a delegation from this Parliament, made up of the presidents of all the political groups, and the largest of the delegations to go to Auschwitz, will participate in the ceremony in tribute to those victims, together with former prisoners, Heads of State or Government of many countries and some of the soldiers who liberated the camp. In that way, we will be paying tribute to the victims, but, above all, we will be remembering that evil that led to the deaths of millions of Jews merely because they were Jews, and of ethnic minorities, homosexuals and political prisoners of various nationalities. It is an evil that affects all of us. Of course it affects the victims and their descendants, but it also affects those of us who were not there, those of us who cannot remember because we did not see it. Auschwitz should remind us of the battle between remembering and forgetting, the battle of memory against something we would like never to have happened, because people who forget their history are destined to repeat it.
The Holocaust is a great problem for the whole of humanity. It is not just a problem for the Nazi murderers and the Jewish victims. Its roots are deeply embedded in some of the characteristics which have frequently shown their hideous face throughout human history. Today, 60 years later, we must continue to fight everything that made it possible: racism, anti-Semitism, xenophobia, interracial hate, the indifference of our society, which believes that it has nothing to do with it, until it finally realises that it does, that it also affects it, but by then it is too late.
To that end, and so that we do not forget it, we shall also vote today on a resolution on the memory of the Holocaust and anti-Semitism.
Ladies and gentlemen, we have the obligation to work every day, not just when the fascination of round figures, 60 years, – why 60 and not 59? – revives the memory, but every day, so that the values of our Constitution – peace, human rights, respect and tolerance – which are entirely contrary to what happened in Auschwitz, are spread and defended in schools, at work, on the stairs, in the street, in the bars, in everybody’s shared daily lives. Remembering Auschwitz offers us an opportunity to defend the values of our Constitution and to take this opportunity to defend human dignity, which was so horrifically violated in that place.
Ladies and gentlemen, I would ask that we observe a minute’s silence.
<omit>(Parliament stood and observed a minute’s silence)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='3'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s3' language="UNKNOWN"> Ladies and gentlemen, following that moment of respect in memory of the victims of Auschwitz, the sitting is suspended.
<omit>(The sitting was suspended at 9.10 a.m. and resumed at 10.00 a.m.)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<chair>IN THE CHAIR: MR VIDAL-QUADRAS ROCA
Vice-President</chair>

<heading number="5">Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="6">Voting time</heading>
<omit>Recommendation Brok (A6-0011/2005) – EU-former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia and EU-Croatia Stabilisation and Association Agreements (Rule 131 of the Rules of Procedure)</omit>
Recommendation Barón Crespo (A6-0007/2005) – Additional Protocol to EU-Chile Association Agreement (Rule 131 of the Rules of Procedure)
Recommendation Rübig (A6-0002/2005) – Multiannual Community programme to make digital content in Europe more accessible, usable and exploitable
Joint resolution by six political groups on the situation in the Middle East   
  <intervention ref='4'>
<speaker>
<name>Wurtz</name>
<affiliation EPparty="GUE-NGL"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s4' language="FR">Mr President, we have come to an agreement with different groups in order to find a compromise acceptable to the majority.
The compromise contains two points. The first part of our amendment would become an addition, while the second part would be the subject of a separate vote. The wording that we are putting to the vote would therefore strongly encourage President Abbas to demonstrate his willingness to bring the violence to an end and would welcome the measures taken by President Abbas with this in view. The rest of the wording remains unchanged.
The second part of the amendment, that is to say the phrase whereby the Israeli authorities are asked to accept and implement the roadmap and the resolutions of the United Nations Security Council, would be the subject of a separate vote.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='5'>
<speaker>
<name>McMillan-Scott</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s5' language="EN"> Mr President, as colleagues realise, this resolution largely deals with the results of the very happy election in Palestine on 9 January when 28 colleagues observed the elections, chaired by myself and with Mrs Napoletano as deputy chairman. The resolution we are voting on not only deals with the approval of the election itself, but also the follow-up we expect the various organisations and institutions to take. Paragraph 15 is inappropriate in this context. It deals with the internal procedures in the European Parliament. I have discussed with Mrs Napoletano and others the necessity to delete paragraph 15. My invitation to the House is to delete paragraph 15.
</speech>
</intervention>  
<omit>Joint motion for a resolution on anti-Semitism and racism</omit>

<intervention ref='6'>
<speaker>
<name>Sonik</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s6' language="PL">This amendment would affect the text as follows. Firstly, there would be a specific reference to the estimated number of victims who died at Auschwitz, some one and a half million persons. Secondly, the amendment provides for a reference to the 15 000 Russian prisoners who died there. I ask you to support this amendment.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='7'>
<speaker>
<name>Ludford</name>
<affiliation EPparty="ALDE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s7' language="EN"> Mr President, he is speaking on the wrong paragraph. He should be speaking on paragraph 5, indent 2, which is the wording in Polish of the Auschwitz-Birkenau Museum. Mr Sonik has just spoken on recital A, but he is supposed to be speaking on paragraph 5, indent 2.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='8'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s8' language="UNKNOWN"> Mr Sonik, there has been some confusion. What you must present now is your oral amendment to paragraph 5, indent 2, but you have presented something else. So please now present your oral amendment to paragraph 5, indent 2.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='9'>
<speaker>
<name>Sonik</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s9' language="PL">That is the case. I apologise for the mistake. The amendment does indeed concern the inclusion in the resolution of a reference to the National Auschwitz-Birkenau Museum at Oświęcim as a special Holocaust education and remembrance centre, along with the Holocaust Centre in Berlin.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='10'>
<speaker>
<name>Schulz</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PSE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s10' language="DE">Mr President, I should like to table an oral amendment to recital A. A number of discussions have taken place over the past few days and during the past hour, and I can perhaps go some way towards ending them by briefly explaining this amendment.
It is undoubtedly true that we are all faced with a difficult situation, in that on days like today every word must be weighed very carefully. Whichever wording is used, our primary consideration must be the victims’ dignity and the perpetrators’ guilt. In order to take everyone’s concerns into account, I therefore propose that we amend the second phrase of recital A, the original of which read; ‘the 60th anniversary of the liberation of Hitler’s Nazi death camp at Auschwitz-Birkenau...’.
We propose that ‘Hitler’s Nazi’ be replaced by ‘Nazi Germany’s’, with the text then reading; ‘...Nazi Germany’s death camp at Auschwitz-Birkenau...’.
As I see it, this would convey Germany’s guilt and special responsibility, whilst at the same time making it clear that it was the Nazis who placed themselves under the burden of this guilt. It is a fact that there were German victims too, and this wording also commemorates them. I therefore ask the House to vote in favour of this amendment.
<omit>(Applause)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='11'>
<speaker>
<name>Poettering</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s11' language="DE">Mr President, after the many debates on this issue, I should like to confirm that the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats will vote in favour of this oral amendment.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='12'>
<speaker>
<name>Ludford</name>
<affiliation EPparty="ALDE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s12' language="EN"> Mr President, could we have some clarity on this subject? There are two separate amendments here. The first – the oral amendment from the PPE-DE Group that Mr Sonik moved – is to the change the wording, which, in English, would now read: ‘a combined total of up to 1.5 million Jews, Roma, Poles, Russians and prisoners of various other nationalities and homosexuals’.
Could we please vote on that first, before we come to the separate issue, that Mr Schulz has just spoken on, of Amendment 1 by the UEN Group to replace, in English, the phrase ‘Hitler’s Nazi death camps’ with ‘German Nazi death camps’.
Two separate votes are required here. With respect, the confusion has arisen not least owing to the services, which have put it all on the same line: recital A, oral amendment from the PPE-DE Group, and the amendment from the UEN Group, about which Mr Schulz spoke.
Could we have two separate votes, please, first on Mr Sonik’s oral amendment, and second on the UEN-Schulz-Poettering package?
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='13'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s13' language="UNKNOWN"> Yes, Mrs Ludford, we have three things: the amendment by Mr Sonik, the amendment just proposed by Mr Schulz and Amendment No 1 by the UEN Group.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='14'>
<speaker>
<name>Cohn-Bendit</name>
<affiliation EPparty="Verts-ALE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s14' language="DE">Mr President, Mr Schulz is right; all our words and all their consequences are of enormous importance. One thing is certain; Mr Schulz’s amendment has nothing to do with the amendment tabled by the Union for Europe of the Nations Group, and should be regarded as an entirely separate issue, because the amendment tabled by the Union for Europe of the Nations Group contains unacceptable statements that we cannot and do not wish to tolerate. We would therefore ask that there be no confusion over this matter. This was the first point I wished to make.
The second point I should like to make is as follows; we acknowledge that the two largest groups in this House – and rightly so – wish to reach a broad consensus on this issue, and this is why we are able to join this consensus. We would, however, like to stress that some of the discussions that took place on this resolution during preparations for this session were – and are – unworthy. This is a point we must emphasise.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='15'>
<speaker>
<name>Schulz</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PSE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s15' language="DE">Mr President, I believe that there is nothing left to add. If you would put Mr Sonik’s oral amendment and my own oral amendment to the vote – incidentally, the aim of my oral amendment was to supplement the original text and to ensure that the amendment tabled by the Union for Europe of the Nations Group was rejected once and for all – we would have precisely what we want, namely a text that is in keeping with the dignity of this day.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='16'>
<speaker>
<name>Voggenhuber</name>
<affiliation EPparty="Verts-ALE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s16' language="DE">Mr President, Mr Schulz has said that we must weigh every word today to ensure that it does justice to the victims and to the perpetrators’ responsibility. It took a very long time for my country, Austria, to admit its shared responsibility for the crimes of National Socialism. ‘Hitler’s Nazis’, which was the wording used in the first version of this resolution, makes this shared responsibility clear, as it implies that Germans were not the only ones involved. Yet this shared responsibility is blurred again by the wording that has now been proposed.
I do not wish to drag out the debate on the issue, but I think it important that an Austrian should take the floor of this House today to join other Members in deploring his country’s shared responsibility.
<omit>(Applause)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='17'>
<speaker>
<name>Kamiński</name>
<affiliation EPparty="UEN"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s17' language="PL">Mr President, I should like to voice a strong protest against what Mr Cohn-Bendit has just said. It seems to me that his statements were based on a misunderstanding, as he said that some of the content of our amendment, tabled by myself personally, was unacceptable. I cannot think what he meant, as my amendment concerned one single word. I proposed replacing the word ‘Hitler’s’ with the word ‘German’. The Union for Europe of the Nations Group has not tabled any other amendments. One may or may not be in favour of the amendment, but I wish to protest against deeming it unacceptable, because I do not consider that to be the case. I must make it quite clear that my amendment only concerned the inclusion of the word ‘German’. The reason for this is that in recent days the people of Poland have been very upset by references to Polish concentration camps and Polish gas chambers in leading European newspapers. Such references are quite simply incorrect and deeply offensive to the Polish nation. That was the one and only reason for my amendment.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='18'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s18' language="UNKNOWN"> Ladies and gentlemen, we have one amendment presented and some oral amendments. We are not going to go back to a debate on the main substance of the issue.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='19'>
<speaker>
<name>Ludford</name>
<affiliation EPparty="ALDE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s19' language="EN"> Mr President, I can clear up Mr Cohn-Bendit’s confusion. As I understand it, Amendment 1, by the UEN Group, just consists of the words ‘the German’ instead of ‘Hitler’s’. Amendment 1/rev. was withdrawn because it was not accepted by the services. I think Mr Cohn-Bendit is referring to that – if I may say so, a bunch of men is creating a great deal of confusion here by the failure to attend to detail – Amendment 1/rev. was withdrawn and, therefore, the question of deleting words like ‘homosexuals’ is no longer on our agenda. We are dealing with the oral amendment by the PPE-DE Group and then the amendment by the UEN Group – which Mr Schulz seems to be amending again – but not the rest of the revised amendment by the UEN Group, to which I think Mr Cohn-Bendit is referring.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='20'>
<speaker>
<name>Swoboda</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PSE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s20' language="DE">Mr President, ladies and gentlemen, I believe that everyone in this House agrees that all those who took part in this crime – whether they were German, Austrian or of other nationalities – should be condemned, and this is conveyed by the phrase ‘Nazi Germany’. The key point is the responsibility of all those involved, and it is to this responsibility that we must draw people’s attention. I therefore ask that a vote now be held and that Members consider the matter once again. It is not a question of whether it was Germans or non-Germans who were involved; what matters is that we refer to all those associated with the criminal regime of Nazi Germany. This is the gist of Mr Schulz’s amendment, to which Mr Poettering has lent his support.
<omit>(Applause)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='21'>
<speaker>
<name>Landsbergis</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s21' language="EN"> Mr President, after so much consolidation and solidarity in relation to amendments, I will ask you to accept one very small oral amendment to the last line of recital A, concerning only two words. After the reference to victimisation on the basis of race, ethnic origin or religion, it is to insert ‘social classification’. This is because we are insisting that Europe must not forget its own history. Millions were deprived of all their rights, including their lives, for social reasons, the final solution with ‘class enemies’.
‘Social classification’ is a very soft wording and I would ask you to support those two words on the grounds of history.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='22'>
<speaker>
<name>Muscardini</name>
<affiliation EPparty="UEN"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s22' language="IT">Mr President, I only wish to say that Baroness Ludford was right and that her interpretation was correct. However, you did not allow me to speak. It is obvious that there are some mental reservations and discrimination in this House. Mr Cohn-Bendit did not know what he was talking about, as he was referring to an amendment which had not been tabled. I would like our group to be respected in the same way as the other groups, otherwise the racists are the people who speak out of turn.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='23'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s23' language="UNKNOWN"> Mrs Muscardini, at this point we are no longer debating the fundamental ideas. We are voting on amendments. Let us therefore continue with the procedure.
</speech>
</intervention>

<heading number="7">Explanations of vote</heading>
<omit>- Recommendation A6-0011/2005</omit>

<intervention ref='24'><writer>
<name>Queiró</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w1' language="PT">The conclusion of this protocol, in keeping with other similar protocols since May 2004, clearly demonstrates the global impact of EU enlargement.
Nonetheless, these protocols are clearly necessary, because there must be legal uniformity and harmony in the enlarged Union. I therefore voted in favour of the recommendation.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='25'><writer>
<name>Ribeiro e Castro</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w2' language="PT">The purpose of this proposal for a recommendation is to conclude a Stabilisation and Association Agreement between the European Communities and the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia and between the European Communities and the Republic of Croatia, to take account of the accession of the Czech Republic, the Republic of Estonia, the Republic of Cyprus, the Republic of Latvia, the Republic of Lithuania, the Republic of Hungary, the Republic of Malta, the Republic of Poland, the Republic of Slovenia, and the Slovak Republic to the European Union. This is also a consequence of the accession of ten more Member States.
Indeed, the accession of those countries entails a range of legal adaptations, in order that they can be placed on an equal footing in the areas of customs, the economy and competition.
I naturally voted in favour.</writing>
</intervention>  
<omit>- Recommendation A6-0007/2005</omit>

<intervention ref='26'><writer>
<name>Queiró</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w3' language="PT">The conclusion of this protocol, in keeping with other similar protocols since May 2004, clearly demonstrates the global impact of EU enlargement.
Nonetheless, these protocols are clearly necessary, because there must be legal uniformity and harmony in the enlarged Union. I therefore voted in favour of the recommendation.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='27'><writer>
<name>Ribeiro e Castro</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w4' language="PT">The purpose of this recommendation is to obtain parliamentary consent to conclude a Stabilisation and Association Agreement between the European Community and its Member States, of the one part, and the Republic of Chile, of the other part, to take account of the accession of the Czech Republic, the Republic of Estonia, the Republic of Cyprus, the Republic of Latvia, the Republic of Lithuania, the Republic of Hungary, the Republic of Malta, the Republic of Poland, the Republic of Slovenia, and the Slovak Republic to the European Union. This is a necessary consequence of the recent enlargement. The accession of those countries in fact entails a range of legal adaptations, in order that they can be placed on an equal footing in the areas of customs, the economy and competition.
I voted in favour.</writing>
</intervention>  
<omit>- Recommendation A6-0002/2005</omit>

<intervention ref='28'><writer>
<name>Goudin, Lundgren and Wohlin</name>
<affiliation EPparty="IND-DEM"/></writer><writing ref='w5' language="SV">The June List is voting against increasing the appropriations with respect to the Council’s original proposal. Digital content is most efficiently created and made accessible by the market or through decisions at Member State level.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='29'><writer>
<name>Queiró</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w6' language="PT">The balance struck between the sum initially sought by the Commission and the funds made available by the Council, commensurate with necessary budgetary limitations, is a reasonable one. I therefore voted in favour.
Most importantly, however, the eContent programme – in common with other similar initiatives – should be an effective means of enhancing the information- and knowledge-based society.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='30'><writer>
<name>Ribeiro e Castro</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w7' language="PT">As well as contributing towards the Lisbon Strategy and towards reinforcing Europe’s competitiveness in the knowledge-based economy, the multiannual Community programme to make digital content in Europe more accessible, usable and exploitable, enables us to achieve satisfactory results in terms of economic growth, job creation, innovation and consumer choice.
This programme is designed for end-users, whether they be ordinary citizens, students, researchers, professionals who want to improve their skills or ‘re-users’ who want to improve or exploit digital-content resources as a profitable activity.
The purpose of the ongoing Community project, as well as to facilitate user access to information, is to transform the content distribution sector and to reinvent the way in which companies, public bodies and governments interact with each other and with the general public.
It is therefore important for the development of Europe’s economy that funding earmarked for the programme making digital content more accessible be raised from EUR 135 million to EUR 149 million. If so, the Community action programme will have a much greater chance of being implemented successfully.
I voted in favour.</writing>
</intervention>  
<omit>- Joint resolution RC-B6-0068/2005</omit>

<intervention ref='31'><writer>
<name>Cederschiöld, Fjellner and Ibrisagic</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w8' language="SV">In welcoming the successful Palestinian election, the European Parliament should firstly emphasise the non-development of democratic structures during Arafat’s time in power. It would also have been desirable to highlight the absence of demands for democratic reforms from other countries, together with the tacit support for undemocratic development in Palestine permitted during Arafat’s time. The presidential election in Palestine was also made more difficult by large groups’ wanting to sabotage the election and, by extension, the democratic process.
The resolution should also place clear demands on the new leadership to implement democratic reforms and should make clear the Palestinian Authority’s responsibility for preventing terrorist acts. At the same time, Israel’s legitimate right to enjoy security and defend its people against terrorist attacks must be recognised. It is important here to emphasise the difference between the Palestinian terrorists’ systematic attacks on civilian targets and the Israeli Government’s interventions against terrorists.
What, finally, are missing are a condemnation of all terrorist acts, including suicide attacks carried out in the Gaza Strip, and an expression by the European Parliament of its deep sympathy for the victims’ families.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='32'><writer>
<name>Goudin, Lundgren and Wohlin</name>
<affiliation EPparty="IND-DEM"/></writer><writing ref='w9' language="SV">The June List supports the peace process in the Middle East and hopes that the parties can soon agree on the Roadmap for Peace. For this to happen, the leaders of both Israel and Palestine must be able to demonstrate statesmanship and political courage.
The June List believes that it is the United Nations that has the main responsibility for mediating between its Member States and for preventing conflicts or bringing them to an end. Throughout history, we have seen how neutral countries have had an important role in this work within the United Nations.
Even if we essentially support the main thrust of the resolution, we do not believe that the EU’s role within foreign and security policy should be extended. We wish to protect Sweden’s freedom of action and the United Nations’ unique position as an international peace organisation.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='33'><writer>
<name>Martin, David</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PSE"/></writer><writing ref='w10' language="EN">. I welcome the reasonably fair and free elections of Palestine and commend the satisfactory manner the elections were conducted despite the circumstances due to the Israeli occupation of Palestinian Territories. The results of the presidential elections should be seen as an opportunity to re-launch negotiations between the Israeli Government and the Palestinian Authorities.
I urge Israel to fully respect the internationally recognised rights of Palestinians and call upon the Council and the Commission to develop another EU observatory mission in Palestine as compliance with the EU-Israeli Association Agreement needs to be enforced, notably Protocol IV of the Agreement.
Israel’s infractions of the Fourth Geneva Convention continue to be a grave concern of the international community whereby constructive efforts of Quartet members acquiescent with Israel and Palestine is imperative for furthering the development of a final and comprehensive settlement of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. The settlement is not only crucial for the Territories themselves but also for the promotion of peace and security for the whole of the Middle East and Arab World.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='34'><writer>
<name>Queiró</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w11' language="PT">I voted in favour of this joint resolution essentially because I agree that, as things currently stand in the Middle East, in particular in Palestine, there is a unique opportunity finally to resume the peace process. Against this backdrop, the balance-sheet on the Palestinian electoral process is in credit.
There are some aspects, however, from which I should like to distance myself. The international community, and the EU in particular – cannot treat the State of Israel, the Palestinian Authority and the so-called ‘armed Palestinian groups’ as though they were equals. A democratic state cannot be bracketed in the same category as terrorist groups. Such obfuscation is unacceptable.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='35'><writer>
<name>Ribeiro e Castro</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/></writer><writing ref='w12' language="PT">The Middle East conflict has been the cause of frequent instability and tension, and the international community has been dragged into repeated attempts to alleviate the political and economic deterioration that the region has undergone for a number of years.
Abu Mazen’s election as President of the Palestinian Authority has given fresh impetus to the relaunch of the diplomatic process in the region. The new Palestinian leader has the opportunity to instigate new political dialogue with Israel, based on criteria of democracy, fairness and mutual respect, in which terrorism is something to be combated and effective and lasting peace is a goal to aim for.
In this new era that has just begun, it is also important that Israel gives signs of hope, good will and cooperation, and pursues its justified and legitimate struggle against terrorism in compliance with the principles of international law.
I voted in favour, in the hope that peace, which goes hand in hand with democracy – long established on the Israeli side and just beginning in Palestine – can finally take root in this most troubled region of the world.</writing>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='36'><writer>
<name>Ries</name>
<affiliation EPparty="ALDE"/></writer><writing ref='w13' language="FR">Dare one talk in terms of a thaw? There is certainly a desire to believe that relations between Israelis and Palestinians are becoming warmer. The signs are there: to begin with, the success of the Palestinian elections, and then the coming to power of Mahmoud Abbas. The man who, in 1993, orchestrated the Oslo Accords has campaigned on the subject of the demilitarisation of the Intifada. This amounts to more than just speeches; it is a conviction that has been constantly reaffirmed. We have also seen the spectacular actions taken by the Palestinian security forces against the terrorists and those forces’ deployment throughout the Gaza Strip, the Israeli moratorium on targeted executions, the re-establishment of diplomatic relations and, today, the announcement by Ariel Sharon of a meeting in two weeks’ time with Mahmoud Abbas. Nor must we forget the support of the United States which, with this second administration of President Bush’s that has resolved to bring the process to a conclusion before 2009, is clearer and easier to interpret. A window of opportunity therefore exists in which the European Union is committing itself more firmly than ever, as evidenced by this election observation mission, the largest ever delegated by the EU. That is what is pointed out in our resolution, which I have voted in favour of, as, at my request, the unacceptable part of paragraph 12, which condemned the indiscriminate terrorist violence from both sides, has been rejected.</writing>
</intervention>  
<omit>- Joint resolution RC-B6-0069/2005/rev.</omit>

<intervention ref='37'>
<speaker>
<name>Vanhecke</name>
<affiliation EPparty="NI"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s24' language="NL">Mr President, I shall be brief. I have abstained from voting on this resolution, obviously not because I do not acknowledge the suffering of the Jewish and other victims of a criminal national-socialist regime, criminal like so many other socialist regimes and dictatorships. I did not vote for this resolution because I only feel disdain for people and politicians who use this suffering for their own party-political ends and for the fight against parties that want to continue to uphold European values and the identity of the European peoples. I also regret that the present resolution does not breathe a word about today’s anti-Semitic terrorism, about today’s anti-Semitic attacks, about the fact that today in our large cities, for example in Antwerp, Jewish people are being attacked by Arabs and Islamists who are today’s anti-Semites. Needless to say, I also regret that the appeal to curb the free expression of opinions was made, because democracy is not possible without it. Finally, I notice that Communists who have never distanced themselves from Communist regimes, which committed acts of terror and boasted concentration camps, were allowed to sign this resolution. I consider this to be a scandal.
</speech>
</intervention>


<heading number="10">Verification of credentials: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="11">Communication of Council common positions: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="12">Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="13">Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="14">Dates for next sittings: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="15">Adjournment of the session: see Minutes</heading>
<omit>(The sitting was closed at 11.05 a.m.)</omit>

</body>

<back>
<update>Last updated: 31 March 2005</update>
<disclaimer>Legal notice</disclaimer>
</back>

</ecpc_EP>

