<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><!DOCTYPE ecpc_EP SYSTEM "ep.dtd"><ecpc_EP><header filename="EN20050127" language="EN"><title>CRE Thursday 27 January 2005</title>

<index>Index

<label>Debates</label>
<date>Thursday 27 January 2005 </date>
<place> Brussels</place>
<edition>OJ edition</edition>

<indexitem number="1">Opening of the sitting</indexitem>
<indexitem number="2">Documents received: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="3">Agenda: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="4">Statement by the President</indexitem>
<indexitem number="5">Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="6">Voting time</indexitem>
<indexitem number="7">Explanations of vote</indexitem>
<indexitem number="8">Corrections to votes: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="9">One-minute speeches on matters of political importance</indexitem>
<indexitem number="10">Verification of credentials: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="11">Communication of Council common positions: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="12">Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="13">Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="14">Dates for next sittings: see Minutes</indexitem>
<indexitem number="15">Adjournment of the session: see Minutes</indexitem>

</index>

</header>

<body>

<chair>IN THE CHAIR: MR BORRELL FONTELLES
President</chair>
<omit>(The sitting was opened at 9.05 a.m.)</omit>

<heading number="1">Opening of the sitting</heading>

<intervention ref='1'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s1' language="UNKNOWN">Ladies and gentlemen, we will have to change the agenda, because, as I expect you already know, the President of Ukraine, Mr Yuschenko, cannot be with us today as planned, due to the weather conditions seriously affecting the whole of central Europe which have prevented him from taking off this morning.
</speech>
</intervention>

<heading number="2">Documents received: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="3">Agenda: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="4">Statement by the President</heading>

<intervention ref='2'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s2' language="UNKNOWN"> We had planned to dedicate a statement and a minute’s silence to the memory of the Auschwitz-Birkenau tragedy today and I believe we must go ahead with that.
Ladies and gentlemen, today is a sad day of commemoration for the whole of humanity. On a day like today in 1945 the soldiers of the Red Army liberated the Nazi extermination camp whose name has become engraved on man's collective memory. It has become engraved on our collective memory as the name of absolute horror, of evil, in its most extreme form, of industrialised, planned and documented crime.
We are still all astounded that it could have happened. But it did happen. It is unimaginable, but it was real. Today, a delegation from this Parliament, made up of the presidents of all the political groups, and the largest of the delegations to go to Auschwitz, will participate in the ceremony in tribute to those victims, together with former prisoners, Heads of State or Government of many countries and some of the soldiers who liberated the camp. In that way, we will be paying tribute to the victims, but, above all, we will be remembering that evil that led to the deaths of millions of Jews merely because they were Jews, and of ethnic minorities, homosexuals and political prisoners of various nationalities. It is an evil that affects all of us. Of course it affects the victims and their descendants, but it also affects those of us who were not there, those of us who cannot remember because we did not see it. Auschwitz should remind us of the battle between remembering and forgetting, the battle of memory against something we would like never to have happened, because people who forget their history are destined to repeat it.
The Holocaust is a great problem for the whole of humanity. It is not just a problem for the Nazi murderers and the Jewish victims. Its roots are deeply embedded in some of the characteristics which have frequently shown their hideous face throughout human history. Today, 60 years later, we must continue to fight everything that made it possible: racism, anti-Semitism, xenophobia, interracial hate, the indifference of our society, which believes that it has nothing to do with it, until it finally realises that it does, that it also affects it, but by then it is too late.
To that end, and so that we do not forget it, we shall also vote today on a resolution on the memory of the Holocaust and anti-Semitism.
Ladies and gentlemen, we have the obligation to work every day, not just when the fascination of round figures, 60 years, – why 60 and not 59? – revives the memory, but every day, so that the values of our Constitution – peace, human rights, respect and tolerance – which are entirely contrary to what happened in Auschwitz, are spread and defended in schools, at work, on the stairs, in the street, in the bars, in everybody’s shared daily lives. Remembering Auschwitz offers us an opportunity to defend the values of our Constitution and to take this opportunity to defend human dignity, which was so horrifically violated in that place.
Ladies and gentlemen, I would ask that we observe a minute’s silence.
<omit>(Parliament stood and observed a minute’s silence)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='3'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s3' language="UNKNOWN"> Ladies and gentlemen, following that moment of respect in memory of the victims of Auschwitz, the sitting is suspended.
<omit>(The sitting was suspended at 9.10 a.m. and resumed at 10.00 a.m.)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<chair>IN THE CHAIR: MR VIDAL-QUADRAS ROCA
Vice-President</chair>

<heading number="5">Approval of Minutes of previous sitting: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="6">Voting time</heading>
<omit>Recommendation Brok (A6-0011/2005) – EU-former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia and EU-Croatia Stabilisation and Association Agreements (Rule 131 of the Rules of Procedure)</omit>
Recommendation Barón Crespo (A6-0007/2005) – Additional Protocol to EU-Chile Association Agreement (Rule 131 of the Rules of Procedure)
Recommendation Rübig (A6-0002/2005) – Multiannual Community programme to make digital content in Europe more accessible, usable and exploitable
Joint resolution by six political groups on the situation in the Middle East   
  <intervention ref='4'>
<speaker>
<name>Wurtz</name>
<affiliation EPparty="GUE-NGL"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s4' language="FR">Mr President, we have come to an agreement with different groups in order to find a compromise acceptable to the majority.
The compromise contains two points. The first part of our amendment would become an addition, while the second part would be the subject of a separate vote. The wording that we are putting to the vote would therefore strongly encourage President Abbas to demonstrate his willingness to bring the violence to an end and would welcome the measures taken by President Abbas with this in view. The rest of the wording remains unchanged.
The second part of the amendment, that is to say the phrase whereby the Israeli authorities are asked to accept and implement the roadmap and the resolutions of the United Nations Security Council, would be the subject of a separate vote.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='5'>
<speaker>
<name>McMillan-Scott</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s5' language="EN"> Mr President, as colleagues realise, this resolution largely deals with the results of the very happy election in Palestine on 9 January when 28 colleagues observed the elections, chaired by myself and with Mrs Napoletano as deputy chairman. The resolution we are voting on not only deals with the approval of the election itself, but also the follow-up we expect the various organisations and institutions to take. Paragraph 15 is inappropriate in this context. It deals with the internal procedures in the European Parliament. I have discussed with Mrs Napoletano and others the necessity to delete paragraph 15. My invitation to the House is to delete paragraph 15.
</speech>
</intervention>  
<omit>Joint motion for a resolution on anti-Semitism and racism</omit>

<intervention ref='6'>
<speaker>
<name>Sonik</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s6' language="PL">This amendment would affect the text as follows. Firstly, there would be a specific reference to the estimated number of victims who died at Auschwitz, some one and a half million persons. Secondly, the amendment provides for a reference to the 15 000 Russian prisoners who died there. I ask you to support this amendment.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='7'>
<speaker>
<name>Ludford</name>
<affiliation EPparty="ALDE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s7' language="EN"> Mr President, he is speaking on the wrong paragraph. He should be speaking on paragraph 5, indent 2, which is the wording in Polish of the Auschwitz-Birkenau Museum. Mr Sonik has just spoken on recital A, but he is supposed to be speaking on paragraph 5, indent 2.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='8'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s8' language="UNKNOWN"> Mr Sonik, there has been some confusion. What you must present now is your oral amendment to paragraph 5, indent 2, but you have presented something else. So please now present your oral amendment to paragraph 5, indent 2.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='9'>
<speaker>
<name>Sonik</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s9' language="PL">That is the case. I apologise for the mistake. The amendment does indeed concern the inclusion in the resolution of a reference to the National Auschwitz-Birkenau Museum at Oświęcim as a special Holocaust education and remembrance centre, along with the Holocaust Centre in Berlin.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='10'>
<speaker>
<name>Schulz</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PSE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s10' language="DE">Mr President, I should like to table an oral amendment to recital A. A number of discussions have taken place over the past few days and during the past hour, and I can perhaps go some way towards ending them by briefly explaining this amendment.
It is undoubtedly true that we are all faced with a difficult situation, in that on days like today every word must be weighed very carefully. Whichever wording is used, our primary consideration must be the victims’ dignity and the perpetrators’ guilt. In order to take everyone’s concerns into account, I therefore propose that we amend the second phrase of recital A, the original of which read; ‘the 60th anniversary of the liberation of Hitler’s Nazi death camp at Auschwitz-Birkenau...’.
We propose that ‘Hitler’s Nazi’ be replaced by ‘Nazi Germany’s’, with the text then reading; ‘...Nazi Germany’s death camp at Auschwitz-Birkenau...’.
As I see it, this would convey Germany’s guilt and special responsibility, whilst at the same time making it clear that it was the Nazis who placed themselves under the burden of this guilt. It is a fact that there were German victims too, and this wording also commemorates them. I therefore ask the House to vote in favour of this amendment.
<omit>(Applause)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='11'>
<speaker>
<name>Poettering</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PPE-DE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s11' language="DE">Mr President, after the many debates on this issue, I should like to confirm that the Group of the European People’s Party (Christian Democrats) and European Democrats will vote in favour of this oral amendment.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='12'>
<speaker>
<name>Ludford</name>
<affiliation EPparty="ALDE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s12' language="EN"> Mr President, could we have some clarity on this subject? There are two separate amendments here. The first – the oral amendment from the PPE-DE Group that Mr Sonik moved – is to the change the wording, which, in English, would now read: ‘a combined total of up to 1.5 million Jews, Roma, Poles, Russians and prisoners of various other nationalities and homosexuals’.
Could we please vote on that first, before we come to the separate issue, that Mr Schulz has just spoken on, of Amendment 1 by the UEN Group to replace, in English, the phrase ‘Hitler’s Nazi death camps’ with ‘German Nazi death camps’.
Two separate votes are required here. With respect, the confusion has arisen not least owing to the services, which have put it all on the same line: recital A, oral amendment from the PPE-DE Group, and the amendment from the UEN Group, about which Mr Schulz spoke.
Could we have two separate votes, please, first on Mr Sonik’s oral amendment, and second on the UEN-Schulz-Poettering package?
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='13'>
<speaker>
<affiliation EPparty="UNKNOWN"/>
<post>President</post>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s13' language="UNKNOWN"> Yes, Mrs Ludford, we have three things: the amendment by Mr Sonik, the amendment just proposed by Mr Schulz and Amendment No 1 by the UEN Group.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='14'>
<speaker>
<name>Cohn-Bendit</name>
<affiliation EPparty="Verts-ALE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s14' language="DE">Mr President, Mr Schulz is right; all our words and all their consequences are of enormous importance. One thing is certain; Mr Schulz’s amendment has nothing to do with the amendment tabled by the Union for Europe of the Nations Group, and should be regarded as an entirely separate issue, because the amendment tabled by the Union for Europe of the Nations Group contains unacceptable statements that we cannot and do not wish to tolerate. We would therefore ask that there be no confusion over this matter. This was the first point I wished to make.
The second point I should like to make is as follows; we acknowledge that the two largest groups in this House – and rightly so – wish to reach a broad consensus on this issue, and this is why we are able to join this consensus. We would, however, like to stress that some of the discussions that took place on this resolution during preparations for this session were – and are – unworthy. This is a point we must emphasise.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='15'>
<speaker>
<name>Schulz</name>
<affiliation EPparty="PSE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s15' language="DE">Mr President, I believe that there is nothing left to add. If you would put Mr Sonik’s oral amendment and my own oral amendment to the vote – incidentally, the aim of my oral amendment was to supplement the original text and to ensure that the amendment tabled by the Union for Europe of the Nations Group was rejected once and for all – we would have precisely what we want, namely a text that is in keeping with the dignity of this day.
</speech>
</intervention>

<intervention ref='16'>
<speaker>
<name>Voggenhuber</name>
<affiliation EPparty="Verts-ALE"/>
</speaker>
<speech ref='s16' language="DE">Mr President, Mr Schulz has said that we must weigh every word today to ensure that it does justice to the victims and to the perpetrators’ responsibility. It took a very long time for my country, Austria, to admit its shared responsibility for the crimes of National Socialism. ‘Hitler’s Nazis’, which was the wording used in the first version of this resolution, makes this shared responsibility clear, as it implies that Germans were not the only ones involved. Yet this shared responsibility is blurred again by the wording that has now been proposed.
I do not wish to drag out the debate on the issue, but I think it important that an Austrian should take the floor of this House today to join other Members in deploring his country’s shared responsibility.
<omit>(Applause)</omit>
</speech>
</intervention>

<heading number="10">Verification of credentials: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="11">Communication of Council common positions: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="12">Decisions concerning certain documents: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="13">Forwarding of texts adopted during the sitting: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="14">Dates for next sittings: see Minutes</heading>

<heading number="15">Adjournment of the session: see Minutes</heading>
<omit>(The sitting was closed at 11.05 a.m.)</omit>

</body>

<back>
<update>Last updated: 31 March 2005</update>
<disclaimer>Legal notice</disclaimer>
</back>

</ecpc_EP>

